原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/eG9pAkRPgNA
原视频发布日期：20200628
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
With part three of my accidental series on abandoned SpaceX projects,
这一期是我意外制作的一个系列 关于SpaceX砍掉的项目的第三部分
It was originally going to be just one video but it kept getting longer and longer.
原本只打算做一个视频 但一直在变长 越来越长
Last episode we finished with Red Dragon
上一期最后谈到了红龙 飞船
which was ultimately dropped in favor of Starship
最终被Starship所取代
and so today I want to start with something sort of related.
所以今天我想先说一些算是相关的东西
Greymon(暴龙兽)
It was informally referred to as Grey Dragon.
它被非正式地称为灰龙
This was a plan announced in 2017
这是2017年宣布的一个计划
to launch a Crew Dragon on a voyage around the moon using the Falcon Heavy
用重型猎鹰发射载人龙飞船进行绕月(掠月)旅行
and carrying a pair of space tourists who were at the time anonymous.
并携带两名当时匿名的太空游客
The mission was slated to occur in 2019
该任务原定于2019年进行
and this resulted in a lot of media interest
而这也引起了媒体的广泛关注
because nobody had sent crew around the moon since the 1970s
因为自上世纪70年代以来 还没有人把宇航员送到月球附近
and SpaceX's schedule would get the tourists.
而SpaceX计划会搭乘乘客
They are ahead of NASA's exploration missions on SLS.
这将比NASA在SLS上的探索任务更早
Coincidentally there had been in rumors of changing the first SLS mission to include crew
巧合的是 曾有传言说要把第一个SLS任务改为载人任务
and this led to the prospect of a space race between NASA professional astronauts and SpaceX tourists.
这导致了NASA专业宇航员和SpaceX游客之间进行太空竞赛的情况
联盟飞船搭载过不少太空游客，但不是专门的任务，所以这里我觉得应该是指主任务为太空旅游
Heck if it happened on schedule it would be the first launch by space tourists in a long time
如果它意外地发生了 这也会是长久以来第一次(专为)太空游客进行的发射
and that raised the bar well beyond anything else,
而这也提高了标准 远远超过了其他人
with potential space tourism competitors like Blue Origin and Virgin Galactic,
比如蓝色起源和维珍银河等潜在的太空旅游竞争对手
offering only short suborbital flights.
它们只提供短期亚轨道飞行
Compared to a regular Crew Dragon launch, the vehicle would be mostly similar
与普通的载人龙发射相比 该航天器将在很大程度上与载人龙发射相似
but would require the Falcon Heavy to deliver the extra Delta V required for translunar injection.
但需要重型猎鹰火箭提供地月转移进入所需的额外速度
The spacecraft would be delivered onto a free return trajectory
该航天器将被送入自由返回轨道
such that no significant maneuvers were required by the Dragon after injection.
以至于龙飞船在进入后不需要进行重大的机动
Just small course correction burns to keep it on course for its encounter with the moon
只需进行小的航向修正点火 使其保持在与月球相遇的航向上
and of course re-entry on the earth.
当然再入地球也是一样
And then in 2018 a day before for the Falcon Heavy launched for the first time,
然后在2018年重型猎鹰首次发射之前的一天
Elon mentioned that Lunar Dragon was no more.
马一龙提到月龙已经不在了
Falcon Heavy had proven to be a more difficult launch vehicle than anyone had expected
事实证明重型猎鹰比预计中的要困难
and the prospect of human rating it for the one and only customer wasn't going to be worth it.
为了唯一的客户 将其进行载人验证是不值得的
Instead there was an even more ambitious plan for the billionaire
另外 对于亿万富翁而言 有一个更具野心的计划代替了它
who want to see the moon from the other side.
一样也是能看到月球背面的那种
It's not really clear how much of this was developed.
并不太清楚这个任务研发了多少
I mean most of the technical developments were already parts of other projects
我是指 这其中大多数的技术发展 已经是其他项目的一部分
so it's possible that almost no work unique to the mission was done.
所以有可能几乎没进行过这个任务中特有的工作
But it was later revealed that the anonymous passenger was gonna be Yusaku Maezawa
但后来发现 这个匿名乘客是前泽友作
who would later upgrade his lunar flight plans to Starship instead.
他后来把月球旅行的计划升级为了Starship的版本
But just this year spacex won a contract to supply the lunar gateway
但就在今年 Spacex公司赢得了一份月球门户补给的合同
using a Dragon spacecraft launched from the Falcon Heavy.
使用重型猎鹰发射的龙飞船
This is a radically different design from the existing Cargo Dragon.
这与现有的货运龙飞船的设计完全不同
It's called the Dragon XL.
它被称为龙XL飞船
And while the broad structure and appearance of the spacecraft are different
虽然航天器的大体结构和外观都不同
I expect that a lot of the avionics propulsion and power systems are similar
我预计很多航电 推进和动力系统都是类似的
and so it seems likely that there might be some design decisions
因此 似乎可能会有一些设计上的决定
which could have been carried over from Grey Dragon to finally appear in Dragon XL.
会从灰龙上保存到龙XL身上
Moving on.
换个话题
When the original Falcon Heavy was announced,
在最初的重型猎鹰公布的时候
it was planned that it's performance would be enhanced by using propellant cross-feed between the Boosters.
它计划通过在助推器之间使用推进剂交叉输送来增强其性能
Now for those of you who are unfamiliar,
对于那些不熟悉重型猎鹰的人 我来解释下
the Falcon Heavy currently runs the core booster at a lower throttle level.
重型猎鹰目前以较低的节流水平运行芯级(助推器)
So that when the side booster separate, they're still propellant left in the core.
因此 当(侧)助推器分离时 芯级仍然有燃料
But with fuel Cross-feed,
但如果使用燃料交叉输送
there would instead be plumbing from those side booster tanks into the core
他们会让侧助推器储罐中的燃料通过管道输送给芯级
so that the center engines are burning fuel from the side tanks
换句话说也就是芯级会使用侧助推器储罐中的燃料
and when stage separation happens that center core continues with a full load of propellant.
而当(侧)助推器分离时 芯级还是装满燃料的状态
So that fully fueled center core now is able to deliver more mass to orbit.
所以 那个加满燃料的芯级现在能够将更多的质量送入轨道
And the side boosters do have to separate a bit earlier
虽然侧助推器会更早分离
but because they're separating earlier they're closer to the launch site
但由于它们分离得比较早 所以离发射场比较近
so it's actually easier for them to perform the return to launch site maneuver and get recovered.
所以实际上更容易让它们进行返回发射场的机动 并进行回收
So anyway this offers a lot of gains and you know what.
所以不管怎么说 这提供了很多的收益 你猜怎么着
It's a trait that every player of Kerbal Space Program knows and uses all the time.
这是每一个坎巴拉太空计划的玩家都知道并一直在使用的特性
Because in KSP, the propellant in those tanks is literally just a number in a computer memory.
因为在KSP中 这些储罐中的推进剂实际上只是电脑内存中的一个数字
And moving it around is literally decrementing one number in incrementing another.
而移动它 实际上只是增加和减少数字而已
In reality, propellant in tanks. It has mass.
在现实中 储罐中的推进剂 有质量
It has viscosity and moving it around involves kinetic energy and momentum.
它有粘度 而移动它 涉及动能和动量
Especially when you're talking about moving it quickly enough to feed very thirsty rocket engines
特别是当你在谈论以足够快的速度来移动它 以满足火箭发动机的庞大需求的时候
and so all that means some very serious plumbing and a lot of development that just wasn't gonna be worth it.
所以这一切都意味着一些非常重要的管道 和大量的开发 但会是不值得的
Cross-feed was quietly dropped from the Falcon Heavy.
交叉输送被悄悄地从重型猎鹰上放弃了
Again probably in large part because Falcon Heavy turned out to be more complicated than expected.
同样可能在很大程度上是因为重型猎鹰比原来预期的复杂
But even without this difficulty, its development wouldn't have been necessary
但即使没有这个难度 它的开发也是没有必要的
because it's not clear that the extra capability would have expanded the potential market for the rocket.
因为不清楚额外的能力是否会扩大火箭的潜在市场
A lot of the early mass estimates were based on the smaller 1.0 based of Falcon 9.
早期的很多运力估计都是基于较小的1.0版猎鹰9号
And when the upgraded first through Full Thrust and then to the Falcon 9 Block 5,
而在全推力以及随后的猎鹰9号第5代升级之后
the mass limits got high enough
质量极限已经足够高
that in fact they were able to move some of the Falcon Heavy payloads over to Falcon 9.
事实上 他们能够移动一些重型猎鹰的有效载荷到猎鹰9号上
And that left Falcon heavy with even fewer payloads
这样导致重型猎鹰的有效载荷就更少了
and adding the fuel cross-feed capability would have raised its ultimate mass capabilities
而且燃料交叉输送的能力 虽然最终能提高其运载能力
but there aren't really any extra customers that would be unlocked by increasing the mass limit.
但这样做不会获得更多的客户
And say a customer did come along such as NASA wants you to launch something extra heavy to lunar orbit.
而如果真的有客户来了 比如NASA希望你发射一些超重的东西到月球轨道
They would be able to get extra mass capability by expanding parts of the Falcon Heavy boosters.
他们就可以通过一次性使用重型猎鹰的助推器来获得额外的运载能力
So that's a lot more reliable ways of increasing your mass
所以(一次性使用)才是更可靠地增加运载能力的方法
and therefore getting fuel cross-feed capability just simply isn't justified.
因此 获得燃料交叉输送的能力只是简单地不值得
the customer is paying the extra cost for a disposable launch system.
客户(本来就)要为一次性发射系统支付额外的费用
So being able to make it non disposable for a handful of customers just wasn't worth it.
所以能够为少数客户提供非一次性的服务是不值得的
But you know on top of that in both the cases I've talked about so far
但你知道 除了我目前谈到的这两个案例之外
the prospects of future development were also diminished because of Elon's big plans for ITS
(重型猎鹰提升运力的)未来发展前景也因为马一龙的ITS大计划而黯然失色
also known as BFR also known as Super Heavy and Starship.
ITS又称BFR也称超重助推器和Starship
And while these are definitely still the future,
虽然这些肯定还是未来的发展趋势(而尚未实现)
it's worth noting that SpaceX originally was planning to build these out of carbon fiber composites.
值得注意的是 SpaceX原本计划通过碳纤维复合材料来建造这些新火箭
And of course that's now been dropped in favor of the current stainless steel design.
当然现在已经放弃了 改用不锈钢设计
So yes, SpaceX had developed the technology to fabricate large carbon composite propellant tanks
所以是的 SpaceX已经开发出了制造大型碳纤维复合材料推进剂储罐的技术
and they tested one of these to destruction on a barge.
他们在一艘驳船上对其中一个进行了破坏性测试
They began building out a facility to manufacture the massive structural components in the port of LA
他们开始在洛杉矶港建造一个设施来制造巨大的结构性部件
And in April 8 2018, Elon shared a photograph showing
而在2018年4月8日 马一龙分享了一张照片 其中显示
the tooling for the 9 meter wide rocket sections with the Tesla parked next to it for scale.
用于制造9米宽的火箭分段的设备 旁边还停了辆特斯拉 用于对比尺寸
In September 2018 during the dear moon presentation,
在2018年9月亲爱的月球 演讲期间
we got some images of a tank section produced by this facility
我们得到了一些该设施生产的储罐部分的图片
with Yusaku Maezawaa standing inside the massive component
前泽友作站在巨大的构件内
and then just before Christmas 2018
然后就在2018年圣诞节前
we started to see some people at Boca Chica building a stainless steel tank
在博卡奇卡 我们开始看到一些人在建造一个不锈钢罐子
that would of course become the hopper test vehicle.
当然之后变成了Starhopper测试飞船
Carbon fiber was dropped for many reasons.
碳纤维被放弃的原因很多
The steel was cheaper.
钢材更便宜
The designs could be modified more easily during development
在开发过程中可以更容易地修改设计
and still handled the range of temperatures
并仍能处理较大的温度范围
between the cryogenic propellants and the furiously hot re-entry plasma
像低温推进剂那样的低温和炽热的再入等离子体那样的高温之间的范围
much better than the carbon fiber.
甚至比碳纤维还好
It was stated that with the right choice of Steel,
据了解 在这样的对钢材的正确选择之后
the improvements in strength at cryogenic temperatures
在低温下强度的提高
would let it match the strength to weight ratio of the high-tech carbon fiber composite for a fraction of the cost.
会让它与高科技碳纤维复合材料的强度重量比相匹配 而成本却只有一小部分
And so the carbon fiber concept was dropped.
于是 碳纤维的概念被放弃了
The tooling was scrapped and SpaceX ended their lease with the port of LA.
制造碳纤维的设备被取消 SpaceX对洛杉矶港的租约也被取消了
And finally we want to talk about recovery and reuse of the Falcon 9.
最后我们要谈谈猎鹰9号的回收和重复使用问题
So SpaceX has already figured out booster recovery and reuse
那么现在SpaceX已经想好了助推器回收和重复使用的办法
and their fairings or sometimes recovered and reused too.
而它们的整流罩有时也会被回收并重复使用
So the last big component is the second stage.
所以最后一个大部件就是第二级
And Elon's regularly talked a bit trying to recover the second stage.
马一龙经常说要回收第二级
The problem is recovering anything from orbital velocity is exceptionally difficult.
问题是要从轨道速度中回收任何东西都是非常困难的
In large parts due to atmospheric heating during re-entry.
很大程度上是由于再入期间的大气加热
And that's made harder
而更难的地方在于
by the second stage having this big fragile merlin engine with the vacuum nozzle at one end.
二级有这个大的脆弱的梅林引擎 它的另一端是真空喷嘴
the first time we saw a video showing a potential way of recovering the second stage was in 2011.
在2011年 第一次看到视频显示 一个潜在的回收二级的方法
The video showed a heat shield on the front of the stage behind the payload adapter
在这个视频中 二级的前面 也就是载荷适配器的后面有一个热护盾
and the vacuum Merlin engine would have the nozzle extension be retractable.
而真空梅林发动机的喷嘴延伸部分可以伸缩
So it could be protected from the aerodynamic forces.
这样它就能免受空气动力的影响了
There would be a, you know, landing legs.
你知道的 还会有一个着陆腿
There would be landing thrusters.
以及着陆发动机
And yeah this was all back in 2011 they looked at this concept.
是的 他们早在2011年就在关注这个概念
But by 2014 it had pretty much been acknowledged that this probably wasn't gonna happen.
但到了2014年 大家就得知这是几乎不会发生的
And the second stage recovery was on the back burner.
而二级的回收被搁置了
Then in 2017 it came back with Elon making some tweets about a giant party balloon and a bouncy house.
而在2017年 它又回来了 在推特 马一龙发了一些关于充气屋和巨大派对气球的消息
That is using a balloon as a hypersonic parachute a device known as a balut.
就是用气球作为高超音速降落伞的一种装置 称为气球降落伞
And then having a ship catching the stage on airbags or nets rather like the fairings.
然后让一艘船用气囊或网抓住二级 就像整流罩一样
So baluts are favored in hypersonic braking because they're more robust than parachutes.
那么气球降落伞在高超音速制动中更受青睐 因为它们比降落伞更可靠
They can be inflated to the correct shape even in a vacuum.
即使在真空状态下也能被充气成正确的形状
So they've been investigated for a long time for helping with re-entry.
在再入大气层的领域 它们已经被研究了很久
But, yeah that whole plan nothing ever really happened from it besides some talking and design profile ideas.
但是 是的 整个计划 除了一些谈话和设计轮廓的想法之外 并没有真正发生过什么
What happened was that faded away because Starship became the focus.
后来因为Starship成为焦点 这件事就慢慢消失了
And that's not before Elon then said that there would be plans to launch a Falcon 9 scale version of the Starship
而这之前马一龙就说过 将计划推出猎鹰9号比例的Starship
to test the re-entry aerodynamics.
来测试再入空气动力学
Put that on a Falcon 9 and have it perform a re-entry.
把它放在猎鹰9号上 让它再入大气层
But that too appears to have disappeared
但那似乎也已经消失了
as SpaceX has gone full steam ahead on rapidly prototyping full-scale Starship and Super Heavy.
由于SpaceX已经全力以赴地快速制造全尺寸的Starship和超重型助推器的原型
So at this point I think we're safe to say the recovering the second stage of Falcon 9
因此 在这一点上 我想我们可以肯定地说 回收猎鹰9号的第二级
is probably an abandoned project.
可能也是一个废弃的项目
just like all the other things I've covered here.
就像我在这里介绍的所有其他概念一样
But you know there's no shame in being an abandoned concept right.
但你知道作为一个被抛弃的概念并不丢人吧
All these ideas on their own are fine ideas with good work put into them.
所有这些想法本身都是很好的想法 有不少的工作投入
However SpaceX is a business
然而SpaceX是一个企业
and it's always a case of the concept
而这样的概念
having to balance the cost of development with the expected return on investment.
必须平衡开发成本 与预期的投资回报
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[音乐]
[Music]